Guide to the Alphonse G. Juilland Papers
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Alphonse G. Juilland papers
circa 1960-1990
SC0606
Juilland, Alphonse G.
6 Linear feet
This collection is composed of five series: Juilland's research for and draft manuscripts of his massive lexicon of the novels of Louis-Ferdinand Celine, ultimately divided into CELINE'S VERBS and CELINE'S ADJECTIVES; manuscripts of his other writing, particularly his book, ELIZABETH AND LOUIS, a history of the love affair between Celine and Elizabeth Craig; his articles and essays on the subject of track and field sports; lecture notes for his course "Introduction to Existentialism"; and publications written by others which he found instrumental to his own research.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Gift of Alphonse G. Juilland.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
Alphonse Juilland, born in 1922 in Bucharest, studied at the University of Bucharest, graduating in 1945 magna cum laude, and obtained his doctorate from the Sorbonne in Paris in 1951. He taught literature, language, linguistics and philosophy in France, Switzerland, Canada, and, in the United States, at the University of Washington, the University of Pennsylvania, and Columbia University, before his appointment as a professor in the Department of French and Italian at Stanford in 1961. Juilland was an international pioneer in his studies of the application of structural methods in historical linguistics and in linguistic structure theory, gaining acclaim as one of the first linguists to analyze language using quantitative methods using computers. His many pioneering works include the first structuralist history of French pronunciation, the first inverse dictionary of the French language, and various books and essays studying the French novelist Louis-Ferdinand Celine's life, fiction, and linguistic importance. In 1975 and again in 1988, Juilland was decorated by the French government in recognition for his major contributions to French culture and education in the United States. Later in life, he became one of the world's fastest senior sprinters, holding three world records for men over 50. Alphonse Juilland died June 30, 2000, at the age of 77.
Description of the Collection
This collection is composed of five series: Juilland's research for and draft manuscripts of his massive lexicon of the novels of Louis-Ferdinand Celine, ultimately divided into CELINE'S VERBS and CELINE'S ADJECTIVES; manuscripts of his other writing, particularly his book, ELIZABETH AND LOUIS, a history of the love affair between Celine and Elizabeth Craig; his articles and essays on the subject of track and field sports; lecture notes for his course "Introduction to Existentialism"; and publications written by others which he found instrumental to his own research.
Access Terms
Celine, Louis-Ferdinand, 1894-1961 --Language.; Juilland, Alphonse G.; Stanford University. Department of French and Italian. Faculty.; French language.; Track and field.
Collection Contents
- Papers
  - Céline Glossary: Research and Drafts
    - Céline Glossary – alphabetized index cards (words, quotes, sources) 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Céline Glossary – alphabetized index cards (words, quotes, sources) 2 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Céline Glossary – brief quotes A(cademie) – Z(ola) (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Céline Glossary – notes (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 1, pp. 2-102 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 1, pp. 103-203 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 1, pp. 204-303 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 1, pp. 304-403 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 1, pp. 404-425 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 2, pp.1-211 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 2, pp. 212-425 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 3 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Céline Glossary – Draft 4 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Céline's Adjectives – Draft 1 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Céline's Adjectives – Draft 2, A-I (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Céline's Adjectives – Draft 2, J-Z (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Céline's Adjectives – Draft 3 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Céline's Adjectives – Draft 4 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Céline's Verbs – Draft of 'Cabotiniser – Dynamer' (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Other Writings
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 3 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 4 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 5 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 6 (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 7 (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 8 (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 9 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Chapitre 10 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Les Entretiens (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Premier Entretien (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Deuxième Entretien (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Troisième Entretien (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Quatrième Entretien (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Cinquième Entretien (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Elizabeth and Louis – Sixième Entretien (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - "The Glottophobic Polyglot, or Céline and Foreign Languages" – Draft 1 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - "The Glottophobic Polyglot, or Céline and Foreign Languages" – Draft 2 (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - Louis-Ferdinand Céline "Lettere a Elizabeth," 1990 (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - "The Enigma of Gypsy Philology," 1996 (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - "A Celinian Trove: Elizabeth Craig's Jewelry Box," 1991 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - "Elizabeth Craig Talks About Louis-Ferdinand Céline" (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Elizabeth and Louis press release (in French), 1994 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - Essays and Articles on Track and Field
    - "Foundations of Track and Field" (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - "The Future of Track and Field" (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - "The Men's Mile" (Box 8B, Folder 1)
    - "Track and Field on Trial" (Box 8B, Folder 2)
    - "Twelve Irreverent Letters on Track and Field" (Box 8B, Folder 3)
    - "Why Do We Run the Distances We Do?" (Box 8B, Folder 4)
    - "Alphonse Juilland's Track and Field Letter," issues 1, 3, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 12 (Box 8B, Folder 5)
    - Juilland, Rethinking Track and Field; the future of the world's oldest sport (SEP Editrice, 2002) (Box 8B, Folder 6)
  - Course Notes
    - Introduction to Existentialism – course notes/ lectures [1 of 2] (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Introduction to Existentialism – course notes/ lectures [2 of 2] (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Publications by Others
    - Cellard and Rey. Dictionnaire du Français NONconventionnel. (Box 9, Folder 3)
    - Luce, Stanford. A Glossary of Celine's Fiction. (Box 9, Folder 4)
    - Sharp, Michael. Célinian Verbs: A Glossary (Box 9, Folder 5)
    - Dauphin and Godard. Cahiers Céline 1 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Dauphin and Godard. Cahiers Céline 2 (Box 10, Folder 2)
    - Céline. Arletty, jeune fille dauphinoise. (Box 10, Folder 3)
    - Cau, Jean. Céline est-il encore maudit? (Box 10, Folder 4)
    - Jamet, Claude. La Céline Comédie. (Box 10, Folder 5)
    - del Perugia, Paul. Céline et les Cuirassiers. (Box 10, Folder 6)
    - Mazet, Eric. Céline: d'un peintre à l'autre. (Box 10, Folder 7)
    - Debrie, Nicole. Céline et L'agité du Trou de Balle… (Box 10, Folder 8)
    - Debrie, Nicole. Céline et L'agité du Trou de Balle… (Box 10, Folder 9)
    - Debrie, Nicole. Cantilènes et Grelots. (Box 10, Folder 10)
    - Debrie, Nicole. Thrènes. (Box 10, Folder 11)
    - Monnier, Jean. Elizabeth Craig Raconte Céline. (Box 10, Folder 12)
    - Tributes to Alphonse Juilland (Box 10, Folder 13)
    - Pinaud, Yves. "As Du Sprint et de la Littérature Française" (Box 10, Folder 14)
  - Other Material
    - Diskettes: drafts of work (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Diskettes: drafts, other computer disks, track and field disks (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Audio Tapes (2): "Beketch, October 31, 1990" (Box 12, Folder 2)
- Papers, Accession ARCH-2001-192
  - Elizabeth Craig photographs (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Colette Destouches photographs (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Ben Tankel photographs and documents (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Lee Klinger collection photographs and documents (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Eric Mazet photographs and drawings (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of France (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Photographs (miscellaneous) (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clippings (miscellaneous) (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Juilland's documents and photographs (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of dancers (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Celine photographs (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth Craig photographs (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Photographs of dancers (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Viola Swisher (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Photographs (Slides) of Europe/France (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Photographs of France (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Photographs of art and jewelry (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Destouches material (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Elizabeth Craig letters (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Photographs of street scenes [Los Angeles] (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (duplicates, scans) (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Negatives (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Photographic proofs (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Photographic proofs (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Tankel II, 1988 Sep 13; 3.1; 1 audiocassette(s) (microcassette) (Box 3)
  - Tankel, Eliz. Interview (Third), 1988 Aug 16; 3.2; 1 audiocassette(s) (microcassette) (Box 3)
  - Mrs. Tankel, 1988 Oct 21; 3.3; 1 audiocassette(s) (microcassette) (Box 3)
  - VI ["When celine approached you...?"], 3.4; 1 audiocassette(s) (microcassette) (Box 3)
  - Seller's Voice, 3.5; 1 audiocassette(s) (microcassette) (Box 3)
  - Craig, [1988?] May 5; 3.6; 1 audiocassette(s) (Box 3)
  - Elizabeth Craig letters and documents (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Elizabeth Craig photographs (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Elizabeth Craig drawings (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Celine negatives (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Alphonse Juilland - Celine miscellany (Box 4, Folder 5)